FARHAN SARESHWALA

hello@fsaresh.com \(\rightarrow \) Capitola, CA 95010

SUMMARY

Staff software engineer with 9+ years of backend development experience and 2+ years of management experience. Experienced in mentoring teams on testing practices/test-driven development, operational excellence in metrics and monitoring, and improving maintainability and extensibility of code.

EXPERIENCE

Tech Lead Manager / Software Engineering Manager

Doma

April 2021 - Present

Remote/San Francisco, CA

After transitioning to a tech lead manager role, I managed and mentored five engineers on the Task Automation team while continuing to contribute to automating title production features, focusing on roadmap completion and management, architecture and code reviews, and operational excellence.

- Reduced time-to-close by title production associates by 25% via automating title production features in Python and Django, coordinating with data science team and internal stakeholders.
- Architected and led project to automate opening title production orders upon email receipt, reducing time to open order by over 90%; coordinated work across three engineering teams and two data science teams.
- Identified areas of improvement on team and made process improvements around project estimation, collaboration, and other team-specific cultural aspects:
 - Introduced and documented responsibilities of epic lead role when taking on new projects, giving engineers more ways to express ownership and become more involved in the planning process.
 - Implemented sprint process changes (e.g. formulaic sprint capacity estimation) that increased average sprint commitment to completion ratio by 24% and sprint velocity by 15%.
- Refined team backlog (scrum) on a weekly basis with feedback/input from product manager and stakeholders to keep team on track to meet deadlines established in quarterly roadmap.
- Conducted biannual performance evaluations for my team going over technical skills and communication; discussed evaluations, promotions, and expected hiring with engineering leadership.
- Guided team through role reductions in team and department, addressing concerns around morale, financial, and roadmap implications. In personal time, supported former colleagues in job search with resume reviews, interview guidance, and networking.

Staff Software Engineer

Doma

March 2020 - April 2021

Remote/San Francisco, CA

Joined Task Automation team, empowering team to automate title production features. Started as one of three engineers on the team, grew Doma Document Intelligence product from proof of concept to critical automation resulting in reduction of 15% of time-to-close needed by associates.

- Served as technical lead and staff engineer for team working in Python/Django, conducting architecture reviews, mentoring engineers on best practices, and acted as a technical point of contact for team.
- Architected system to abstract out and automate calculating recording fees, reducing time spent by internal closing team by 80%. Gathered requirements from stakeholder teams and coordinated to parallelize work.
- Led expansion of existing projects and led new projects, including estimation, implementation, and coaching engineers on team; coordinated with data science team, product managers, and external stakeholders.

- Onboarded four team members and one intern to the team, introducing them to points of contact, new resources, and building any new documentation needed arising from questions asked during onboarding.
- Led several investigations and postmortems into product issues including surfacing updates to management, coordinated with impacted/responsible teams for mitigations, resolutions, and prevention strategies.
- Guided team through cloud platform migration from Heroku to Azure, including container-izing several applications and coordinating with larger cloud platform migration team.

Senior Software Engineer

May 2019 - March 2020

Birst, an Infor Company San Francisco, CA

Worked on Business Intelligence Engine team, improving internal SQL-based query language and data processing engine in Java with MongoDB, along with library code for data encryption and authentication.

- Added secure credential encryption to core product, including adding REST APIs to support external applications and migration path for existing customers. Followed software development life cycle, including integrating, testing, and externally documenting these updates with core product features.
- Found and fixed bugs in lexing and parsing affecting customer scripts using internal query language.
- Supported customers by resolving multiple support calls, working with internal support escalation team.

Senior Software Developer

August 2015 - May 2019

AVEVA, FKA OSIsoft San Leandro, CA

Worked on Core Libraries team on internal libraries written in C++ and C# supporting networking, data structures, and APIs directly used by three other teams within the company.

- Led effort to migrate from Microsoft Team Foundation Server (SVN-based) to Azure Repos (Git-based), educating and aligning team on branch strategies and release patterns.
- Redesigned build, release, and test infrastructure in Azure DevOps, replacing soon-to-be deprecated infrastructure; created documentation for other teams making this migration later in the year.
- Designed, implemented, tested, and maintained internal library distribution via NuGet packages used by upstream, internal teams within the company.
- Acted as technical and social leader to interns and new hires by guiding them through complex sections of the codebase and teaching best practices, modern coding standards, and test driven development.
- Added and tested Transport Layer Security using certificate-based authentication, replacing previously insecure authentication protocol. Acted as subject matter expert during security audit of new protocol.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming Languages

Python, Java, C++ (11, 14, 17), C#

Frameworks & Tools Other Technologies

Django, Kubernetes, Docker, PostgreSQL, Terraform, nginx, Tomcat

Azure, AWS, Heroku, Jenkins, CircleCI, Postman

EDUCATION

University of California, Davis

September 2011 - June 2015

B.S. in Computer Science

B.A. in Psychology